The דף daf is כח, Kuf-Ches, 28; we pick up at the
very bottom of כז עמוד ב Kuf-Zayin Amud-Beis and we had been
dealing with the issue about going to a non-Jewish doctor to be
healed, where we saw that the גמרא Gemara was very concerned about
the issue of danger, that was its reality or its perception of
reality, should say, to the point that, you know, this wasn't, this
was so much that they were willing to say that unless you
feel, unless it's a situation which you think you'll definitely die unless
you get, you know, medical attention, that even if you think that
there's a risk you're going to die, you should better not get
that attention, rather, you know, better not go to the doctor rather
than go to a non-Jewish one. So clearly the גמרא Gemara very
much believed that there was a grave danger involved in this. So,
and then we had a whole fascinating discussion about what happens if
you're dealing with like heresy and so on and maybe even in
that case, if, you know, even if you think you're going to
die, that's so dangerous, and then an issue about, a very important
issue about חיי שעה, chayei sha'ah, that if somebody is terminal that
they are allowed to take certain risks, you know, between protecting the
last short amount of time they have to live as opposed to
undergoing some type of a treatment that might extend their lives and
so on, that's obviously extremely important in terms of issues about הלכה,
halachah, medical הלכה. halachah. We now pick up at the bottom but
with that in mind about this issue about going to a non-Jewish
doctor, we pick up at the bottom where it says
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, two lines from the bottom. אמר רבא בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן כל מכה שמחללין עליה את השבת אין
מתרפאין בהן.
Amar Rava bar bar Chana
amar
Rabbi Yochanan kol maka she'mechalelin aleha es HaShabbos ein mitrapin bahen. If
it is something that is a, that is dangerous, that is a
danger to life, and how would you measure that the thing you're
dealing with is a danger to life? It's the type of thing
that you could violate שבת Shabbos in order to take care of,
attend to. So clearly it's a type of a wound that represents
a danger to life; that you can't go to them because again,
you're afraid. Now that, by the way, if it's a danger to
life, there you could sort of say that the concern is maybe
not even so much that they're going to exacerbate it as that,
as that they just that they won't help it, you know, sufficiently.
Okay, but anyway, but he's limiting this issue to going to certain
with certain issues that are obviously, you know, that are, that are
a serious danger. Last line of
כז עמוד ב: Kuf-Zayin Amud-Beis: ואיכא דאמרי אמר רבא בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן כל מכה של חלל אין מתרפאין מהן. Ve'ika d'amri
amar Rava bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan kol maka shel chalal
ein mitrapin mehen. If it is a wound that is on the
inner side of the body as opposed to an external wound, an
internal wound, then you cannot go to them again for a similar
issue because it might represent a life danger. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What difference is it? Because in general
anyway, we rule that any internal wound is a wound that is
a life danger, so effectively it's two ways of saying the same
thing, that if it's a dangerous type of an issue don't go
to
them. So איכא בינייהו גבא ידא וגבא רגלא. ika beinaihu gava yada
v'gava ragla. The difference would be something on the outside of the,
the back of the hand or the, you know, the outside of
the leg where actually that is not an internal wound and nevertheless
it is a type of a thing that you actually could violate
שבת Shabbos for. So of course the question is that if it's
a type of thing that you could violate שבת Shabbos and it
represents a possible risk of life, then why can you go to
them if it's if you're afraid, you know, that they're going to
exacerbate it or not help it or so on? So רש"י Rashi
says well because it's an external type of a wound, if you
see it's getting worse, you can go ahead and then go get
it treated by someone else, you know, you could apply some salve.
So because it's external, even though it's a sort of, you know,
a potential, you know, serious danger, you know, you're not afraid that
you're going to die there in the doctor's office, you're just afraid
again that maybe they won't do everything that's necessary or, you know,
they'll do something that might be
counterproductive. But רש"י Rashi says at least according to this approach, at
least if it's external, you'll be able to see it and maybe
do something about it in time. Now I should mention that this
whole גמרא Gemara that draws a line between whether you can go
to a non-Jewish doctor only for things that are potentially, you know,
life-threatening and not for things that are minor, that's okay, I should
say things that are minor and not life-threatening you can go to
a non-Jewish doctor, that actually is against the גמרא Gemara yesterday. You
might remember the גמרא Gemara yesterday, right, we had this statement of
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that said I won't even go to them
if I have an ache because of a wound that was made
for bloodletting. And the גמרא Gemara actually gave that as evidence that
you actually are not allowed to go to them even if it's
not life-threatening. So this גמרא Gemara seems to be operating on a
different approach. This גמרא Gemara seems to be saying no, actually if
it's not life-threatening it's okay, it's only a problem if it's life-threatening.
תוספות Tosafot tries to reconcile the two גמרות, Gemaros, but I think
it's simpler to just read it that these two גמרות Gemaros are
taking different approaches: one is you can't go to them for anything,
and the other is it's only for things that are life-threatening. Okay,
so now I have to warn you that pretty much the rest
of this גמרא Gemara is going to be on the one hand
it'll be important issues about drawing the line about what types of
things you can be מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. Okay, so for like
what types of wounds or illnesses or whatever are considered severe enough
that you can be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. On the and then
we're going to get into though a whole list of rabbinic remedies,
okay, so prepare yourself. Okay, so anyway the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, איכא בינייהו גב ידיה וגב רגליה, Ika beinaihu gav yadei
ve-gav raglei, דאמר רב אדא בר מתנה אמר רב, de-amar Rav Adda
bar Matna amar Rav, גב ידיה וגב רגליה gav yadei ve-gav raglei
הרי הן כמכה של חלל ומחללין עליהן את השבת. harei hen ke-maka
shel challal u-mechallalin aleihen es ha-Shabbos. So in the back of the
hand or the, you know, back of the leg, it's like an
internal injury and you can be מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, but it's
like an internal injury but that doesn't mean that it is an
internal injury and therefore that might be a difference whether you can
go to a non-Jewish doctor for this. Okay. אמר רב זוטרא בר
טוביה אמר רב, Amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav, כל מכה
שצריכה אומד מחללין עליה את השבת. kol maka she-tzricha omed mechallalin aleha
es ha-Shabbos. Anything that is bad enough that you have to like
get an assessment of wait a minute, oh my god, is this
possibly life-threatening? You know, the גמרא's Gemara going to say like somebody
has a very high fever, right? 104, 105, so you know, when,
you know, parents obviously get extremely worried. Oh my god, this seems
like it might be life-threatening. Sometimes doctors say no, don't worry about
it, you know, that's happened sometimes and other times they say yeah
bring him into the emergency room, right? So anything that you need
some assessment like that is you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos and this
is an important principle that basically even ספק פיקוח נפש מחללין את
השבת. safek pikuach nefesh mechallalin es ha-Shabbos. Even something that might be
in the category of life-threatening, you don't even know for sure, but
the fact is that you need to assess that's already enough to
be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. כל מכה שצריכה אומד מחללין עליה את
השבת. Kol maka she-tzricha omed mechallalin aleha es ha-Shabbos. אמר רב שמן
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav Sheman bar Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan, והאי אשתא צמירתא, ve-hai eshta tzmireta, see I didn't give the
high fever as just an
example, you know, out of nowhere. This very high fever, כמכה של
חלל דמי מחללין עליה את השבת. ke-maka shel challal dami mechallalin aleha
es ha-Shabbos. That's like an internal injury, you're מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos,
somebody has a very high fever. A very fascinating issue comes up,
you know, about, on the one hand, things that aren't in the
גמרא Gemara but that we know are life-threatening, obviously we'll say or
potentially we'll be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. How about things that are
in the גמרא Gemara but like we feel nowadays are not life-threatening?
I that you can you still go ahead and be מחלל שבת
mechallel Shabbos for that? You know, some פוסקים poskim say like yeah
if it's in the גמרא Gemara you can go ahead and do
it, others are more hesitant. So anyway, but certainly high fevers can
be very dangerous. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. מהיכן
מכה של חלל? Me-heichan maka shel challal? So where does a מכה
של חלל maka shel challal begin? What's considered
internal? פירוש רבי אמי מן השפה ולפנים, Perush Rabbi Ammi min ha-safah
u-lefanim, from your lips inside. So anything even inside your mouth.
Even like a bad toothache.
Yeah, well the גמרא Gemara is going to get, yeah the גמרא
Gemara is going to get to that. Okay, anything inside the internal
part of your
body. Wonder how about if you've got some ear infection or something
like that. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי רבי
אלעזר, Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, ככי ושיני מאי? kachi ve-shinei mai? What about
ככי ושיני? kachi ve-shinei? So שיני shinei are your teeth, exactly Michael's
question. What are ככי? kachi? רש״י Rashi seems to say ככי kachi
are like your jaws, you know, or the part inside where your
teeth
are.
Maybe the whatever, yeah the part inside that your teeth are connected
to. I mean that's your jaw, but the jaw we usually think
about the external. The gums I guess. The gums, yeah the gums,
okay. The gums. תוספות Tosafos says that ככי kachi might refer to
like the your bigger teeth. I don't know, what are your bigger
teeth? Your molars or something. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos says it's two
types of teeth. תוספות Tosafos says it's molars and your maybe front
teeth. רש״י Rashi says it means your gums and your teeth. Okay.
ככי ושיני מאי? Kachi ve-shinei mai? So do we say now, what
do you mean that's inside the from the lips inside. So no,
here's the
question. כיון דאקושיה נינהו, Keivan de-akushye ninhu, כמכה דבראי דמו. ke-maka de-barai
damu. Since they're hard, maybe it's external, right? Because because it's like
you know these are really solid, so maybe it's not like it's
going to get into your internal organs or
something. או דלמא כיון דגואי קיימי, O dilma keivan de-gevai kaimei, כמכה
של חלל דמו. ke-maka shel challal damu. It's like an internal injury,
some infection maybe it'll spread inside to your internal organs or something.
אמר אביי תא שמע, Amar Abaye ta shema, come and hear. החושש
בשיניו, Ha-choshesh be-shinav, if somebody has some toothache, לא יגמע בהן את
החומץ, lo yigma bein es ha-chometz, you can't sort of drink vinegar
in order to dull the toothache. Now that's because on the one
hand, right, the rabbis are very lenient, I mean not lenient, whatever,
they're, as רב חיים Rav Chaim used to say, they're very מחמיר
machmir on פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. They say any possible risk of
life you violate even a דאורייתא De-Oraisah prohibition on שבת Shabbos for
the to save a life. On the other hand when it's a
minor issue when it's called a מיחוש בעלמא, michush be-alma, it's a
minor issue then they say you're not allowed to do certain types
of רפואות, refuos, certain types of like, you know, medical treatments. Actually
I should point it out because this distinction gets lost in the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara seems to feel like there's you know
our גמרא Gemara we're going to read makes it sound like there
are only two levels but there really are three levels. There's like
there's like ספק safek you know פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and obviously
higher פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh obviously. Okay, so that you violate that
you
violate even a דאורייתא. De-Oraisah. Okay, on שבת Shabbos for the to
save a life. I don't know what this board has, like, it
has measles or something. Okay, anyway, that's like level one. Then you
have a that's a מכה דבראי, maka de-barai, external מכה. maka.
Then you have a חולה כל הגוף choleh kol ha-guf which is
you know you've got like the flu, whatever, you're lying down in
bed, you've got some, you know, it's not something trivial. And then
I'll get back to that in a minute and then what you
have is מיחוש בעלמא. meichush b'alma. מיחוש בעלמא meichush b'alma is an
ache, a headache, a toothache, you know, something like that. So מיחוש
בעלמא meichush b'alma actually is forbidden to do to do even even
מדרבנן, m'derabanan, you
know,
yeah, דרבנן derabanan forbidden even to do, you know, permissible I mean
meaning it would otherwise be permissible
medical treatment. So meaning for example like a good example of this
is that you can't take like aspirin,
you
know, swallowing vinegar
is
a case we're dealing with, any you know any type of a
thing that's considered a medical treatment they made it rabbinically forbidden even
if it's only a tiny thing. Here, okay, so here actually the
big line comes here. You go from allowing things to forbidding things.
There's almost like no place in between. Okay, that's the big line.
And חולה כל הגוף choleh kol haguf is basically what you're you're
allowed to do obviously permissible medical treatments, so obviously permissible medical treatments
you can do.
Yeah, but that's sort of tautological.
Well, no, only only tautological because I made a middle category.
Okay.
No, because here you're allowed forbidden to do permissible
medical treatments. No, permissible means it would have been forbidden were it
not for this דרבנן. derabanan. Aspirin is the most clear. But what
you're also allowed to do is certain you can violate certain דרבננים.
derabananim. There's a question which
דרבננים. derabananim. Okay, אמירה לגוי amira l'goy certainly. Telling a non-Jew is
certainly in there. Okay, so here you're allowed to actually violate things,
you know, biblical things, rabbinic things, and so on. Once you get
to a מיחוש בעלמא meichush b'alma it actually gets like the opposite.
You're not even allowed to do things that otherwise would have been
permissible like aspirin and something like this. Okay, now actually I should
what's the difference in חולה כל הגוף? choleh kol haguf? Well, if
you it's a if it's a serious headache, חולה כל הגוף choleh
kol haguf is something that basically is defined as you would want
to lie down for, like something that you feel even if you're
up and around it's so terrible you really just want to go
go go lie down in bed, right? So that's essentially חולה כל
הגוף. choleh kol haguf. So some type of like a splitting headache,
okay, would be in here. Some type of a you know of
a just like whatever a headache headache you know is here. Now
the problem of course that everybody has the problem here that everybody
has here is like really on שבת Shabbos I'm supposed to go
around feeling miserable? Like this is crazy. Why won't you let me
do things that otherwise would be permissible? And the גמרא Gemara explains
that it's a concern that if we let you take medicines and
so on, particularly this is mostly I should say it starts with
an idea of medicines because שחיקת סממנים, shechikas samamanin, right right right
no medicines because you had
you didn't go just go to the medicine cabinet you had to
go to the,
right you had to go ahead and you had to and exactly
you had to grind the stuff and so on and therefore and
that's why they didn't want you to do it. But the but
the cost is that you're feeling terrible on שבת. Shabbos. So there's
definitely a lot of פוסקים poskim nowadays that because the reason is
no longer relevant because you just have this stuff you know whatever
in bottles that they actually find a way to extremely extremely narrow
this case and to say that like no almost nobody is in
a מיחוש בעלמא meichush b'alma category. That's like what some פוסקים poskim
try to do.
But anyway did you say that רב משה Rav Moshe said that
like you know that anything that you know, that's that's a story
about רב אויערבאך. Rav Auerbach. Anyway moving on. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא
שמע. ta shma. Okay so now we're trying to prove this issue
about teeth. So תא שמע. ta shma. אמר אביי תא שמע Amar
Abaye ta shma come and hear. החושש בשיניו לא יגמע בהן את
החומץ. Hachashesh b'shinav lo yigma bahen es hachometz. If you've got a
if you've got a toothache don't swallow vinegar. That's in this bottom
category. Okay חושש הוא דלא choshesh hu d'lo
that's only if you've got a toothache. הא כאיב ליה טובא ha
ke'ev lei tuva if you have a so I mean if it's
a little bit a little annoying, okay not you know but if
it's serious if it's a serious painful seriously painful so שפיר דמי
shapir dami you could swallow vinegar. Now the point is big deal
you could swallow vinegar. That's not our question. If you said oh
it's seriously annoying you're allowed to do it that only proves that
it's in this middle category. We're trying to prove that if you've
got a serious problem with your teeth it's considered a פיקוח נפש
pikuach nefesh and you can violate שבת. Shabbos. Okay so that we
really haven't proven. אביי Abaye seems to have eliminated this middle category.
Anyway the גמרא Gemara answer rejects it for a different reason. The
גמרא Gemara says דילמא תנא היכא דכאיב ליה טובא חושש נמי קרי
ליה. dilma tanna heicha d'ke'ev lei tuva choshesh nami kari lei. You
don't know what the תנא's Tanna line is when he says toothache.
Toothache might not mean a minor toothache. Toothache might mean even if
it's a serious ache you know a serious pain in the tooth
or whatever so you know sometimes maybe that also constitutes to toothache.
So the גמרא Gemara says you don't know from that תנא Tanna
if it's a serious problem in the teeth whether it whether it
goes you know to this category the גמרא's Gemara even ignoring this
middle category or even rises to the category of פיקוח נפש. pikuach
nefesh. That we can't tell. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. תא שמע ta shma come and hear. We're still trying to
prove this issue about teeth, teeth and gums. רבי יוחנן חש בצפדינא.
Rabbi Yochanan chash b'tzaftina.
He had this problem of צפדינא tzaftina which was again some type
of a of a tooth disease or tooth problem. אזל לגבי דההוא
מטרוניתא, Azal l'gabbei d'hahu matrunisa, he went to this non-Jewish woman, Matron,
that's the word, מטרוניתא, matrunisa, Matron. עבדא חמשא ומעלי שבתא, Avda chamisha
u'mallei shabsa,
she treated him on Thursday and Friday. אמר לה, Amar lah, and
it was a three-day treatment, and he said to her, למחר מאי,
L'machar mai, I can't come to you on Shabbos. What should I
do? אמרה ליה, Amra leh, she said to him, לא צריכת, Lo
tzrichat, you won't need it, two days is enough. So he said
to her, אי צריכנא מאי, Ei tzrichna mai, what if I do
need it? אמרה, אישתבע לי דלא מגלית לה, Amra, Ishtava li d'lo
maglit lah, swear to me that you will not reveal this secret
treatment. This is how I make my money, my פרנסה, parnassah, is
I know how to do this treatment for teeth. So if I
tell you, swear to me that you won't tell anybody. So אישתבע
לה, Ishtava lah, so he swore to her, לאלהי ישראל לא מגלינא,
L'elohei Yisrael lo maglina, to the God of Israel I shall not
reveal it.
גליא ליה, Galya leh,
so she revealed it to him. למחר, L'machar, the next day which
was Shabbos and he gave a major שיעור shiur to the community
on Shabbos, נפיק דרשה בפרקא, Nafik darsha b'pirka, he went and he
said what a great opportunity, I've got the whole community here. I'm
going to tell them, hey, if anybody ever has any problems with
their teeth and has this gum disease that I had, here's the
way you can heal it. Because he figured that part of a
rabbi's responsibility is not just giving a sermon on the פרשה, parsha,
part of a rabbi's responsibility is being concerned about the health of
the community. Somebody told me that he knows a rabbi that on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur he got up and he says, you all
have to go check the batteries in your smoke detectors, and then
he sat down. So okay, so anyway, so this is he's learning
from רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, והא אישתבע לה, v'ha ishtava lah, he swore to her. So
how could he do that? So he says, no, here's what he
meant. לאלהי ישראל לא מגלינא, L'elohei Yisrael lo maglina, I'm not going
to reveal it to the God of Israel. אבל לעמי ישראל מגלינא,
Aval l'amei Yisrael maglina, but to His nation Israel I will reveal
it. So obviously he was, it's sort of like אנכי עשו בכורך.
Anochi Esav bechorecha. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא איכא חילול
השם. v'ha ika chillul hashem. It's all very nice, technically you found
a loophole. Isn't this a desecration of God's name? You're swearing in
the name of God and then you reveal it? What does that
make her think about how you relate to God, you know, to
taking an oath in the name of God and how you feel
about your God? So the גמרא Gemara says דגליא ליה מעיקרא. d'galya
leh mei'ikara. No, after she told him, he said, oh, by the
way, you should know that oath I just took, what I said
in that oath was I won't reveal it to God but... so
therefore it's not a חילול השם chillul hashem since he דגליא ליה
מעיקרא, d'galya leh mei'ikara, meaning obviously. The point is, it's very funny
that the גמרא Gemara thinks that once she realizes that he's not
violating his oath, it won't be a חילול השם. chillul hashem. The
fact that a Jew used a deceptive way of saying something that
made it sound like he was promising in order to get this
secret information and then to reveal it, that's not the חילול השם.
chillul hashem. The חילול השם chillul hashem is just that she thinks
that he violated his oath. Now that she understands he didn't violate
his oath, no חילול השם. chillul hashem. I can't explain that, go
figure that one out. Okay, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
yes
what does the note say?
Yes, says that either she committed suicide or she converted to Judaism,
there are two different...
Oh, wonderful, that makes the story so much better. Alright, anyway. Oh,
converted to Judaism because I see these Jews know how to, you
know, sneak out, how to like weasel out this information, okay, under
false pretenses.
They said that because he publicized the cure for free to the
public when he could have used it to earn money.
Oh, he's such a צדיק. tzadik. Okay, fine.
And the suicide was because she lost her control over...
No kidding. Okay, anyway. Okay, אלמא כמכה של חלל דמיא. Alma kemaka
shel challal damya. So you see anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
והא איכא חילול השם, v'ha ika chillul hashem, so אלמא כמכה של
חלל דמיא. alma kemaka shel challal damya. You see it's like a
מכה של חלל. maka shel challal. Why do you see it's like
a מכה של חלל? maka shel challal? So because he was willing
to go get treated, he was willing to do the treatment on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so since the point was he wanted to know
what treatment to do on שבת, Shabbos, he was willing to do
the treatment on שבת, Shabbos, you see it's in the category of
פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Again what is fascinating is that the גמרא
Gemara is not considering the possible middle category here. There could be
some types of treatment you do on שבת Shabbos that you're not
doing biblical violation. It doesn't prove it to the level of פיקוח
נפש. pikuach nefesh. This גמרא Gemara is fascinating that it seems to
ignore this whole middle category. Okay, and therefore it's saying that if
you're doing this treatment on שבת, Shabbos, it proves that it is
a פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמא כמכה
של חלל דמיא. alma kemaka shel challal damya. So אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, no, שאני צפדינא, shani tzaphtina,
this particular gum disease... how do they translate what disease we're talking
about? Did they say anything there?
This
particular gum disease is different, הואיל ומתחיל בפה וגומר בבני מעיים. ho'il
u'matchil b'peh v'gomer b'vnei mei'ayim. This thing really is internal. This thing
is a type of a gum disease that can spread into your
internal organs. But this does not prove that any problem with your
teeth, right, if you've got, you know, some I don't know, you
know, inflamed gum or whatever it is, you know, certain types of
gum disease, sure, they're real risks, they could, you know, there's a
disease and it could spread. But it doesn't mean that everything with
your teeth is a פיקוח נפש.
pikuach nefesh. Anyway, you asked about צפדינא. tzaphtina. Yes, this says some
commentators explained it's from some sort of decay or some sort of
contraction or compression. But here he says is interesting, the description is
internal... Scurvy. That would be interesting. Okay. So folks have actually been
discovering more and more now how much that what is in the
mouth
affects this whole all our systems, right,
in modern. Really? Alright well that's fascinating because as like because actually
that is the conclusion that anything in the mouth actually, I mean
the גמרא Gemara says the mouth. The only question in the גמרא
Gemara was would it even include teeth and gums. Yeah but.
Right, which is why sailors used limes for it.
Dental hygiene and cleaning is so important because because it infects the
whole body right, it goes right into the internal organs. אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. Okay, we just did
that. Okay now מאי סימניה? Mai Simanei? So we never had a
black and white answer to the issue about the teeth and the
gums but the basic assumption is that yes anything inside the mouth
is a פיקוח נפש. Pikuach Nefesh.
פיקוח נפש, Pikuach Nefesh, I guess vinegar is something people just wouldn't
be taking regularly is that it? Yeah you don't use... like okay
now take vinegar.
No because the משנה Mishna says you can dip your bread in
vinegar, you can do it like a normal person would eat it
but you can't go ahead and like swish around with the vinegar
and hold it by your gums in a way that it's obvious
that you're doing it for רפואה. Refuah. Okay מאי סימניה? Mai Simanei?
What are the signs of this disease, this צפטינא Tzaftina which maybe
or which maybe we're saying now
is scurvy. So רמי מידי בי ככאי ומייתי דמא מבי דרי. Rami
midi bei kachai u'maisei dama mibei dari. When you put something between
your teeth or your gums or whatever then blood will come out
from between the rows of your like even if you you know
of your other teeth. Okay so it cause bleeding of bleeding of
the gums. ממי הוי? Mimei hava? What causes
it? מקרירי קרירי דחטי Mikarirei karirei de-chitei from very cold wheat or
רש"י Rashi says as if you eat wheat I think רש"י Rashi
says when you're very cold, but it sounds like it's saying very
cold
wheat. ומחמימי חמימי דסערי U'me-chamimei chamimei de-sari and very hot barley or
רש"י Rashi says I think if you're very hot you eat barley.
Both or one of the other?
I don't know, I don't know, no I don't think both, just
barley. ומשייורי כסא דהרסנא U'mishi-yurei kassa de-har-sana if you eat the like
leftovers, the remnants, the dregs of this fish hash. Okay that'll cause
this. So go figure that out.
Hey he says here a diet is comprised exclusively of grain based
foods and fish is likely to lead to severe depletion of vitamin
C in one's body.
Oh if you only eat that stuff. Alright that's that's a creative
interpretation. If you only eat that then you're not getting your vitamin
C so that's the problem. Okay anyway מאי עבדת ליה? Mai avta
lei? So what do you do to heal it or what did
she do for him? What okay now that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
went ahead and announced it tell us what the secret
is. So אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא, Amar Rav Acha b'rei de-Rava,
מי סאורא ושמן זית, Mei se-ora u-shemen zayis, water from sourdough and
olive oil. ומלח U-melach and salt and I guess you rub it
on the gums. ומר בר רב אשי אמר, U-mar bar Rav Ashi
amar, משחא דאוזא, mishcha de-avza, the fat you know of a goose
like... Sounds like שמאלץ. schmaltz. Yeah well basically what it is you
know a what is it called reduced? Not reduced. What's it called
when you turn it into a liquid? Rendered. Rendered thank you, rendered
fat. בגדפא דאוזא Be-gadfa de-avza which you use a wing of the
of the goose to actually apply it. I don't know why you
need a feather. Feather. I meant a feather excuse me feather of
the goose to apply it. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אנא עבדי כולהו,
ana avdi kulu, I tried all of those things ולא איתסאי v'lo
itzsai and I didn't get healed. עד דאמר לי ההוא טייעא Ad
amar li ha-hu taya until a certain like nomad said to me,
אייתי קשיתא דזיתא aisei kashita de-zeisa take like a olive pit דלא
מלו תילתא de-lo malu tilsa that's not a third ripe וקליה אמרא
חדתא ve-kali-u amara chadata and and like bake it or whatever like
you know grill it over on on on a new shovel
ודביק בי דרי ve-davik bei darei
or something בי דרי. bei de-darei. עבדי הכי avdi hachi I did
that ואיתסאי ve-itzsai and I got healed. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan היכי
עביד הכי? heichi avid hachi? Now how did רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
okay so you explained how he got rid of the חילול השם
chillul HaShem although you didn't really explain that. You explained how he
did it on שבת Shabbos because it was a פיקוח נפש. Pikuach
Nefesh. But how did he go to something that wasn't a פיקוח
נפש Pikuach Nefesh to a non-Jewish doctor which is how he got
into this whole discussion to begin with? Okay היכי עביד הכי? heichi
avid hachi? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן Ve'amar Rabba
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan even it was said in the
name of רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, כל מקום שמחללין עליו את השבת
אין מתרפאין מהן. kol makom she-mechallelin alav es Ha-Shabbos ein misrappin mehen.
Anything that's a threat to life you can't go to to them.
אדם חשוב שאני, Adam chashuv shani, an important person is different. Remember
how the other day we had about אשה חשובה isha chashuva on
דף כ"ה עמוד ב' daf chaf heh amud beis about how that
woman would not have to be afraid of of being murdered and
possibly of and then there becomes the whole question if she has
to be afraid of rape and so on. So here too if
the person is important, important to the you know to the and
is known by the sec- by the secular government, by the non-Jewish
government people are going to be careful with him. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says one minute. והא רבי אבהו דאדם חשוב הוא, Ve'ha
Rabbi Abbahu de-adam chashuv hu, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu was very well
like closely connected to the government ורמי ליה יעקב מינא ve'ramya lei
Yaakov Mina this יעקב Yaakov the heretic again this student of ישו
הנוצרי Yeshu ha-Notzri right he was יעקב Yaakov right that was his
name right? Which apostle?
I
don't know if he's supposed to be an apostle or not I
know that he's a anyway yeah יעקב Yaakov okay anyway סמא אשקייה
sama ashkyei so he put certain type of a salve on his
on his thigh or yeah שקיה shakeh is probably his calf, okay?
Now ואי לאו רבי אמי ורבי אסי דלא חכוה לשקיה, Ve-ilo Rabbi
Ami ve-Rav Assi delo chachuhu leshakeh, and if had they not removed
it by licking it off of his calf, so פסקה לשקיה paskei
leshakeh his calf would have like been destroyed, okay?
And it didn't harm them?
I don't know. Anyway, it's like, you know, it's like when you
suck out a wound that a, you know, a snake bit from
and you spit it out. Anyway, so you see that this he
would have killed him. Okay, so the Gemara says, okay so how
so therefore how even though he was an אדם חשוב? adam chashuv?
So אדם חשוב adam chashuv clearly is not enough. So the Gemara
says רבי יוחנן רופא מומחה הוה. Rabbi Yochanan rofe mumche havah. Now
Rabbi Yochanan, it wasn't just, or really forget the אדם חשוב adam
chashuv answer, the answer was was that the doctor was an expert
doctor and they would not have risked their reputation, like the Gemara
said, you know, before it gave the רופא מומחה rofe mumche answer.
רבי אבהו נמי רופא מומחה הוה, Rabbi Abahu nami rofe mumche havah,
oh Rabbi Abahu's case also was an expert answer doctor. So the
Gemara says no, שאני רבי אבהו דמוקמי ביני בי נשיא. shani Rabbi
Abahu demukmi benei binashayu. Rabbi Abahu was somebody who was always in
fights with the heretics. So therefore, when the heretic had an opportunity
to do something to him, even though he was an expert doctor,
he was willing to risk his whole reputation because now was a
chance to get back at Rabbi Abahu. So he wanted to fulfill
in himself תמות נפשי עם פלשתים, tamut nafshi im pelishtim, you know,
like Shimshon said, let me die with the Philistines. He was willing
to go ahead and risk his reputation because that was a very
special case. But as a general rule, an expert doctor, you know,
will not go ahead and what do you call it and do
something to risk their reputation, so therefore that was allowed but not
because he was an אדם חשוב, adam chashuv, that was not the
answer. I remember when I was in high school, I read this
story about, you know, everybody reads these classic short stories. Anyway, so
I read the story about, I don't remember who wrote it, but
it was about this guy, he's like in the middle of a
whole revolutionary war in some, I think, South American country, and he
goes to this doctor, you know, not doctor, to this barber, you
know, and the barber's going ahead and like, you know, with that
like sharp blade, you know, whatever, and the barber actually is like
from the other side and this guy is the leader of the,
you know, of the competing side, and the whole sort of thing
is like that the barber is like thinking like should I kill
him, shouldn't I kill him, or whatever. Anyway, and then he doesn't
and the guy gets up from his seat and he sort of
says like, yeah, I knew you wouldn't do it, I like he'd
sort of realize like I knew you wouldn't, you know, that you're
an honest man of a profession or whatever. Anyway, so just exactly
this. Okay, anyway, have to find that story. Anyway, yeah.
Why did they notice that this יעקב Yaakov was not the same
one as the one in the?
Why, yeah, why do they say that?
Because they're two different
time periods.
Oh, contemporary of Rabbi Ishmael.
Oh, that's a good point, right,
and he preceded Rabbi Abahu by several generations.
Seven generations. Several, yeah. No, that's a good point, the whole dating
is wrong. תוספות Tosafot asks a question about why before were you
not allowed to go to a heretic for health purposes and here
you were, you know, forget the issue that he's going to do
something bad to you in terms of your health, why aren't we
afraid that the heresy will draw you away like the גמרא Gemara
before? So that's why תוספות Tosafot says before if you remember that
it's only a problem when they're doing the healing with use of
their either עבודה זרה avodah zarah or their heresy and then we're
afraid that it'll sort of draw you away. But if they just
happen to be an idolater or a heretic or whatever, that's not
the problem. The problem is to what degree they use it in
their actual form of treatment. Okay, but yes, that's important, that it's
a different יעקב. Yaakov. Okay, so now the Gemara says like this,
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, האי פדאתא סכנתא היא. hai padasa sakanta hi.
This פדאתא, padasa, which is, I have to remember what all these
things
are, oh right, some type of a wound made by metal. Tetanus?
Yeah, right, exactly. But it's made by like metal, some type of
a wound made through some of a sword or of metal, right?
Obviously that could be a, you know, what could you get, tetanus,
right? Anyway, any type of thing like that is a risk ומחללין
עליה את השבת, umchalelin aleha et ha-Shabbat, so you violate Shabbat. מאי
אסותא, Mai asuta, how what do you do to heal
it? למיפסק דמא תיכלי בחלא, Lemifsak dama tichlei bechala, to get the
bleeding to stop, תיכלי בחלא, tichlei bechala, take I think cress in
vinegar and either eat it or apply it to the wound. לאסוקי,
Le-asukei, in order to get it to to heal, to the skin
to like close up, so גרדא דדיבלא, garda divla, some scraping
of a Rashi says this some type of a grass, some uprooting
of a grass, וגירדא דאסנא, ve-girda de-asna, some scraping off of a
what do you call it off of a thorn bush. Okay, או,
o, or ניקרא מקילקלתא, nikra mi-kilkulta, whatever that guy is, oh right,
type of a worm that is, oh, a worm from the garbage
dump. Okay, I guess, I don't know, do you eat it?
Anyway, maybe,
I mean it's פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, you can violate you can
violate
restrictions. Okay, fine. אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra, האי ענבתא פרוונקא
דמלאכא דמותא היא. hai invasa parvanka de-malcha de-mota hi. This type of
like these like boils that are basically like an ענבתא, invasta, an
ענבתא invasta like a grape, you know, big bulbous boil, is a
harbinger of the angel of death. It's like, you know, the guy
that goes before to make
the announcement. If you bring the letter, you should be the one
to execute it. Okay, so that's that's that that what that what
that line means. Anyway, so he is a harbinger of the angel
of death. מה אסותא? Ma asuta? Just what do you do if
you get to have
this? תיגנא בדובשא, Tigna bidvasha, either you have something in honey, what's
the tigna
here?
עשב, esev, some type of a rue? I don't know. Rashi says
some type of a grass. Some type of a grass in honey,
again, I don't know if this means you eat it or you
apply it. או כרפסא בטילייא, o krafsa bitlaya, or it is something
else in strong wine or Tosafot says weak wine. What does it
say krafsa is?
Wild celery. Now we know. אדהכי והכי, adehachi v'hachi, כרפס, karpas, I
guess, I guess. Okay, while you're waiting to get these
materials, לייתי אינבתא דכמניה, layti invata d'chimneih, get a grape that looks
roughly the same size of this boil, which was which the word
was used was a grape for this
boil, וניגדר עילויה, v'nigdor ilaveih, and rub it on it. חיורתי לחיורתי,
chivarta l'chivarta, if it's a white boil rub it get a white
grape, ואוכמתי לאוכמתי, v'uchmata l'uchmata, if it's a black boil get a
black grape. Amar Rava, that's like sympathetic
healing. אמר רבא האי סימטא פרוונקא דאשתא היא. Amar Rava hai simta
parvanka d'eshta hi. This simta, which is simta normally means like a
can mean like a narrow alleyway, but Rashi says oh it's also
some type of a some type of a what do they describe
it as? Abscess, right, it's also some type of a boil or
some type of a, you know, of a blister or something of
that, okay, a blister
is a harbinger of a fever. מה אסותא? Ma asuta? What should
you do? למימחי שיתין אתקוטי, l'mimchei shitin atkutai, hit it with a
sixty with a with a sixty snaps. Rashi says like if this
is your boil on your hand and you go like this sixty
times against it. I guess you puncture it or something. Okay, that's
the question: do you puncture a boil and try to, you know,
abscess and try to get out the pus? Okay, so that's what
you do. You first of all do that, maybe by doing that
you get all the pus to gather, and then
ולמיקרע שתי וערב, u'l'mikre sheti v'erev, cut it open like, you know,
a crosshatch opening, okay, and then you get out the pus. והני
מילי דלא חיור רישיה, v'hani mili d'lo chivar reisheih, that's only if
the head of it has not turned white, אבל חיור רישיה, aval
chivar reisheih, if the head of it has turned white, לית לן
בה, leit lan bah, it's not a problem. Okay,
it's
not a danger. רב יעקב חש בפיקא. Rav Yaakov chash b'pika. Rav
Yaakov got ill with pika, with this with some type of a
like of a thing in his anus, or presumably it means a
what do they describe it as? Hemorrhoids? Or they don't say? Piga.
Whatever,
no, pika means in his anus. אורי ליה רבי אמי ואמרי לה
רבי אסי אורי ליה, orei leih Rabbi Ami v'amrei lah Rabbi Assi
orei leih, לייתי שבע בני אהלא, layti sheva bnei ahala, go ahead
and get seven basically types of of seeds of ohala. Ohala is
a classic what do they say that is?
Red aloe. Aloe. Oh, aloe!
Aloe's helpful. Yeah. Okay, מור ואהלות, mor v'ahalot, you know, myrrh
and aloe, I guess mor ve'ohala is a classic type of a
salve. Oh, so it makes sense. Aloe, oh, you even see it
in the word. Oh, now I know. Okay, and that's mor, mor
is myrrh, myrrh and aloe. Okay, get seven like seeds of aloe,
טולנא, tulna, red, Rashi
says, וצור ליה בחללא דבית צווארי, v'tzur leih b'chalala d'veit tzavarei, and
wrap it in a type of a cloth that was cut out
of the neck of a garment, you know, when to make the
neck of a
garment, ולכרוך ידיה נירא ברקא, v'lichroch yadeih nira barka, and wrap around
it some type of a string or a hair of a
barka. What do they say that
is? Animal hair. Some animal hair, fine. וטמיש ליה בנפטא חיורא, v'tamish
leih b'nafta chivara, and sort of and submerge it in white naphtha,
white naphtha is what what do they call that? Naphtha, right. וליקלייה,
v'liklayeih, and then burn it. Gasoline.
What? Gasoline. No, I'm just
imagining.
Gasoline. Vaseline comes from petrol. Oh, does it? Maybe, but they're burning
it now. וליקלייה, v'liklayeih, burn it, ובדרי ליה עילויה, u'vadrei leih ilaveih,
and then sprinkle it on it. ואדהכי והכי, v'adehachi v'hachi, now while
you're waiting to get all those materials
together, לייתי קשישא דאסנא, layti kshisha d'asna, go take some type of
a, you know, a seed of a of a thorn bush, ולינח
פיקא להדי פיקא, v'linach pika lahadi pika, and take the cracked part
of the seed and put it against where the skin is cracked.
והני מילי פיקא עילא עילא, v'hani mili pika ila ila, that's only
if the cracked and the rash is on the outside, but פיקא
תתא, pika tata, if it's actually inside the body, so what, what
should you
do? לייתי תרבא דצפירתא, layti tarba d'tzipirta, get the fat of a
goat, דלא איפתח, d'lo iptach, that has not yet had a child,
ולפשר, u'lifshar, and I think it means like, whatever, render it, right,
that's what, and then go ahead ולשדי ביה, u'lishdei beih, and put
it inside the person's anus. Okay. ואי לא ve-ee lo and if
that doesn't work or you don't have those materials, ליתי תלתא טרפא
קרא leisay tlata tarpa kara get three leaves of a gourd
דמייבשי בטולא demyavshei betulla that have been dried out in the shade,
וליקלי velikli and burn them, וליבדר לווייהו velivdar lavyayhu and sprinkle it
on it. ואי לא ve-ee lo and if either that doesn't work
or you don't have
that, ליתי משקדי דחלזוני leisay mishkaday dechalzoney go take something of the
חלזוני chalzone which is like a snail. What does Rashi say משקדי
mishkaday is?
Muscle shells.
Oh, the shells. Okay, the shells of a חלזוני. chalzone. It's interesting
they say it's a muscle because when we talk about it for
anyway, okay, muscle shells ואי לא ve-ee lo and do something with
them. Okay. ואי לא ve-ee lo and if that doesn't work, מייתי
משחא וקירא maysei mishcha vekira take the oil of a of a
of a oil and what do you call it and wax mixed
together
Rashi says, ולינקיט בסחקי דכיתנא velinkot beschakay dechisna and take it in
some type of
worn out garments of
a flax, of linen, בקיטא bekayta in the summer. Okay, I'm
sorry, ולינקיט בסחקי דכיתנא velinkot beschakay dechisna I'm sorry, I read that
wrong. ולינקיט בסחקי דכיתנא בקיטא velinkot beschakay dechisna bekayta and the person,
the way Rashi reads it, should wear linen garments in the summer,
stay cool, ודעמר גופנא ved'amar gufna and cotton garments בסיתווא besitva in
the fall or in the winter, you know, keep warm or keep,
you know, if it's in the winter keep warm, if it's in
summer keep cool.
It doesn't stop with the winter because there's no real...
Right, I know. So right, for us it's fall, for them it
was winter. יישר כח. yishar koach.
But the word is still used in Arabic. Oh really? Which means
rain and the
rainy season and the winter? Huh, okay. Right, because the Gemara really
has two seasons. It has spring-summer and fall-winter, right? Yeah. Okay, so
the Gemara says like this.
It's all fall when it's...
Right, right, right, good point. It never occurred to me. יישר כח.
yishar koach. רבי אבהו חש באודניה Rabbi Abahu chash be-udnay now, so
that was... so those were teeth issues then we had an anus
issue, now we have an ear issue because that's also internal. He
had a problem with his
ears. אורייה רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה בבי מדרשא Oraye Rabbi Yochanan ve-amri
lay be-bay midrasha so either Rabbi Yochanan taught him or they said
what did they teach him in the בי מדרשא? beis medrash? כי
הא דאמר אביי ki ha de-amar Abaye what Abaye said. אמרה לי
אם amra lee aim my mother said to me, לא איברי כולייתא
אלא לאודנא lo ivray kulyasa ela le-udna you know, the kidneys were
created only to heal the ears. Okay, so what does that mean?
We're going to somehow do something with some animal kidneys, right, and
we're going to use it for some for some type of a
medicinal treatment. ואמר רבא ve-amar Rava what did they say
there, anything? No. Kidneys. Okay. ואמר לי מניומי אסיא ve-amar lee Minyumi
asya and Rava said Minyumi the doctor said to me, כולהו שקייאני
קשו לאודנא kulhu shakyany kashu le-udna all types of drinks or either
maybe it means also liquids to apply to the ear are difficult
for the
ear, לבר ממיא דכולייתא levar mimaya de-kulyasa except for the water of
kidneys. So here's what you do. ליתי כולייתא דברחא קרחא leisay kulyasa
de-barcha karcha go get the kidneys of a of a of a
bald goat, of basically a goat that does not have wool or
whatever, does not have
hair, ולקרוע שתי וערב velikro shesi ve-erev and cut them like you
know
hack cross. Okay. ולינח אמללא דנורא velinach a-malala de-nura put it on
a on a coal, on a fire
coal, והנהו מיא דנפקי מיניה ve-hanu maya de-naphki minay and the water
that you know comes from it as it's
burning, okay, לישתינהו באודניה lishtinhu be-udnay put it in the ear. לא
קרירו ולא חמימו אלא פשורי lo kreyru velo chamimu ela pshurey it
shouldn't be cold and it shouldn't be hot, it should be just
right, אלא פשורי, ela pshurey, okay, it should be lukewarm. ואי לא
ve-ee lo and if you can't do that or that doesn't work,
ליתי תרבא דחיפושתא גמליניתא leisay tarba de-chipushta gamlinisa take the fat of
a, okay, what is this, of a חיפושתא chipushta is a beetle.
Yeah, oh, a beetle!
Oh, okay. Iskarbot. יישר כח, yishar koach, you know all these difficult
words. The beetles were חיפוססיי. chipusasay.
I
gotta have you around here, יישר כח. yishar koach. Okay, beetle or
a scarab, okay, a big scarab or big
beetle, וליפשר veliphshar and render it, ולישדי באודניה velishday be-udnay and put
it in the ear. ואי לא ve-ee lo and if you can't
do that or that doesn't
work, למלייה לאודניה משחא lemalaye le-udnay mishcha fill your ear with
oil, ולעביד שבע פתילתא דאספסתא vela-avid sheva ptilta de-as pasta and go
ahead and make seven wicks out of אספסתא as pasta which is
like some type of a fodder. How do they translate אספסתא? as
pasta?
Green wheat stalks.
Green wheat stalks. ולייתי שופתא דתומא ve-laysei shupta de-suma and get also
like the handle of a of a garlic, like I guess it
means the stuff around the garlic, that paper stuff around
the garlic, okay, וליסר בערקא בחדא רישא velisar be-arka be-chada reisha and
go ahead and put a... What is this ערקא arka again Rashi
says? It's decoction used for Mel Francis.
No kidding.
What did they say ערקא arka is? Rashi says it's the hair
of a lice or whatever that means. What did they say after
the after the garlic?
Tie them with animal hair at one end.
Animal hair, fine. Okay, tie it with animal hair בחדא רישא be-chada
reisha at you know at each end or at one end, וליקלי
בהו נורא velikli behu nura and... And light one end with a
fire ואידך רישא v'idach reisha and the other end of the wick
מותיב באודנא mosif b'utna put in the ear where the oil is,
ear where the oil is. I mean I suppose that the point
of this is to try to create some type of a vacuum
or is it heat to transfer heat? Heat, right. Okay. I can
actually see that this actually could do
something. You know. ולותיב אודניה להדי נורא v'luseiv udnei lahadi nura and
put your ear against the fire, I guess close to the fire.
ואיזדהר מזיקא v'izdaher mizika but be careful about the wind. You don't
want your ear to catch fire. ונישקוף חדא ונינח חדא v'nishkof chada
v'ninach chada and as one wick burns out, remove it and put
the other wick in. Okay, and that's then then that's the
treatment. לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way, another version of this treatment
is ואי לא v'i lo if you didn't weren't able to do
the previous thing
ליתי שבע פתילתא דביקרא leisi sheva psilta d'biqra take seven wicks of
this animal hair ושייף להו משחא דאשפסתא v'shayif lehu mishcha d'aspasta and
like you know sort of rub them with oil, דאשפסתא. d'aspasta. Now
I don't know what oil of this green wheat means. What's oil
of wheat? Anyway, I know cream of wheat. Anyway, וניתי חד רישא
בנורא v'neisi chad reisha binura put one of the heads in fire.
What?
I don't know if I have the same spot there. Was it
balsam oil?
That's what it says balsam oil is what it means. דאשפסתא? d'aspasta?
Yeah they say balsam oil. Balsam oil. Okay. Okay, balsam oil. Put
one light one end with a fire וחד רישא באודניה v'chad reisha
b'udnei and the other end in the ear. ונישקוף חדא ונינח חדא
v'nishkof chada v'ninach chada I guess as it gets close to the
ear, remove one wick and place it with the other. ואיזדהר מזיקא
v'izdaher mizika and be careful of the wind. ואי לא v'i lo
and if that stuff doesn't work or you can't do
that, ליתי אודרא דנאדא דלא משקיף leisi udra d'nada d'lo mashkif take
a what is
this? רש"י Rashi says it is garment scraps, dyed garment scraps. It's
like מוך moch I think is down. In modern Hebrew it's down,
מוך moch I think.
What is down? Down, מוכין. mookhin. Right, right.
Oh but מוכין mookhin in the רש"י Rashi in the גמרא Gemara
basically means like I think like a worn-out garment. What do they
translate as? Violet wool that has not been combed.
I'm sorry? Violet wool that has not been combed.
Not been combed. Oh so it is like you were saying. It
is more like down like before it's actually been, okay. שכוח. Shkoyach.
All right, really have to have you here. Okay, so take this
אודרא דנאדא udra d'nada this uncombed wool
דלא משקיף d'lo mashkif that has not been combed, oh there you
go. Okay then that's violet, I don't know how the color matters.
ונינח בה v'ninach bei and put it in the ear
ונתלייה לאודניה להדי נורא v'nislye l'udnei lahadi nura and sort of suspend
it above a fire ואיזדהר מזיקא v'izdaher mizika and be careful of
the wind. Okay, ואי לא v'i lo if that doesn't work, ליתי
גופסא דקניא עתיקא leisi gufsa d'kanya atika בר מאה שנין bar mea
shanin go get a reed like you know of something of a
that's like a hundred years old, a tube of a reed that's
a hundred years old
ולימליה מלחא גלניתא v'limlei milcha galanisa and salt it with this like
type of a rock salt ולקליה v'liklei and burn it ולידבק v'lidbak
and put it against you know and like rub it on the
ear. וסימנך v'simanch and a general principle to remember about all these
various treatments is רטיבא ליבשתא rativa l'yaveshta things that involve liquids, you
know like the oil and whatever, you use if the problem is
a dry ear. The ear is dried up and it's like clogged
or whatever. ויבשתא לרטיבא v'yaveshta l'rativa and the things that are dry
things, like this case about the
reed, is the thing you use for an ear that is like
that is dripping and that is you know and has pus coming
out of it and so
on. Okay, אמר רבה בר זוטי אמר רב חנינא Amar Rabba bar
Zuti amar Rav Chanina we're not done. מעלין אזנים בשבת Ma'alin oznayim
b'Shabbos you can lift up the ears on Shabbos. Some type of
a just like you know treatment, I guess you pull up the
ears. רש"י Rashi says it also means that like somehow there was
some problem with the muscles of the of the cheeks or of
the jaw.
Where were we? תני רב שמואל בר יהודה Tani Rav Shmuel bar
Yehuda ביד b'yad that you can use your hands אבל לא בסם
aval lo b'sam but you can't use some type of a salve.
That's only because not because the גמרא Gemara like this actually רש"י
Rashi says this would be a סכנה, sakana, but if it's possible
to do it in a treatment that's just as good that would
not violate Shabbos, better to do that. איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some
say בסם b'sam no you can use a salve אבל לא ביד
aval lo b'yad not don't use hand. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama מיזרב
זריף mizrav zarif because if you use your hands it'll be it'll
make a wound, like actually like using your hand will actually do
worse than presumably using the using the the type of a salve.
Okay. רש"י Rashi says the salve would only be rabbinic, but the
hand could actually cause some type of a I don't know pull
something and cause some type of
a bleeding. אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב Amar Rav Zutra
bar Tuvia amar Rav עין שמרדה Ayin she'marada now we get to,
we're moving away we now move away from particular ways of healing.
I mean actually this last line also wasn't getting to the details
of the medicinal treatments, the medical treatments. It was talking about like
what are some of the guidelines. You know it's sort of saying
so some problem with the ears and the jaws is a serious
Shabbos problem, but it was also telling you try to do it
in a way that will you know if it's just as good
of a treatment do it in a way that will minimize... minimize
the violation. Now we get to an extremely important discussion about the
status of when a particular, when it might not be a פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh but maybe it's a risk of a limb, okay?
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב, Amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia
amar Rav, עין שמרדה, ayin shemarda, if you have an eye that
is rebelling, okay, you have some problem with an eye, it's inflaming
or whatever, you feel the eye is in
danger, מותר לכוחלה בשבת, mutar lekhochla beShabbos, you can apply this type
of כחלא. kechala. כחלא kechala was a standard type of eye ointment
or treatment or whatever, you can go ahead and apply it on
שבת. Shabbos. Now, that's not so much of a big deal. What
שבת Shabbos violation is there in doing that? So סבר מינה, savar
minei, he assumed what he meant was
הני מילי דשחיק סמני מאתמול, hanei mili deshachik samani me'etmol, that's only
if it's been ground up the day before, so there's no biblical
violation. אבל משחק בשבת ואתויי דרך רשות הרבים לא, Aval mishchak beShabbos
ve'atuyei derech reshus harabim lo, but to do a biblical violation like
to grind it on שבת Shabbos or to bring it through רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, no. He assumed you wouldn't be able to do
a biblical violation. It's an eye, it's not an internal
injury. אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן, Amar lei hahu me'rabbanan, so one of
the rabbis
ורב יעקב שמיה veRav Yaakov shemei said, לדידי מפרשא מיניה דרב יהודה,
lididi mefarsha minei deRav Yehuda, I have a tradition from the name
of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, אפילו משחק בשבת ואתויי דרך רשות הרבים
מותר, afilu mishchak beShabbos ve'atuyei derech reshus harabim mutar, you're even allowed
to grind it on שבת Shabbos and bring it through רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. This is considered a risk to life. Okay, and we're
going to see why in a
minute. רב יהודה שרא למכחל עינא בשבת, Rav Yehuda shara lemichal aina
beShabbos, so this is the tradition of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. He
allowed people to apply this ointment to an eye on שבת. Shabbos.
אמר ליה רב שמואל בר יהודה, Amar lei Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda,
so רב שמואל בר יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda said, I hope
this is not his son because
מאן צאית ליהודה, man tzayis leYehuda, anybody who listens to יהודה, Yehuda,
מחיל שבי, mechal shabei, will be מחלל שבת. mechaleil Shabbos. You cannot
apply this salve on
שבת. Shabbos. ולסוף חש בעיניה, Ulesof chash be'eineih, in the end this
רב שמואל בר יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda himself had some eye
inflammation or whatever on שבת. Shabbos. שלח ליה, Shalach lei, he sent
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שרי או אסור, shari o assur, am
I allowed or not allowed to use the salve? הא, Ha, שלח
ליה, shalach lei, he said back to him, לכולי עלמא שרי לדידך
אסור, lekulei alma shari ledidach assur, anybody else can use
it, you're forbidden. Now one wonders whether he really meant that because,
like, would he really want this guy to have, lose his eye
on שבת? Shabbos? But he was obviously teaching him a lesson. It's
all very nice to give a ruling when it doesn't apply to
you and you don't really feel the need for that, right? It's
all very nice to sit in your comfortable armchair and say, eh,
it's not a פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, it's not a problem. When
it's you and you understand the fear that goes with something like
an eye inflammation or whatever, you'll think differently about it. Okay. וכי
מדידי הוא, Vechie mididi hu, and then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said,
and do you think I was making this up? דמר שמואל היא,
demar Shmuel hi, I got this as a tradition from שמואל. Shmuel.
Okay, that you're allowed to do this and presumably allowed to do
this, the גמרא's Gemara saying, even if it requires a real שבת
Shabbos violation. ההיא אמתא דהויא בי מר שמואל, Hahi amsa dehavya bei
Mar Shmuel, now there was a maidservant that was in the house
of
מר שמואל, Mar Shmuel, דקדחא לה עינא בשבתא, dekadcha lah aina beShabbata,
she had an eye inflammation on
שבת. Shabbos. צוחה, Tzevacha, she was crying out, ולאכא דאשגח בה, veleika
de'ashgach bah, nobody was paying attention to her, nobody was treating her.
פקעה עינה, Paka'ah einah, her eye basically literally popped out or whatever,
you know, she lost her
eye. למחר נפק מר שמואל ודרש, Lemachar nafak Mar Shmuel vedarash, he
got out the next day and he taught the whole
people, עין שמרדה מותר לכוחלה בשבת. ayin shemarda mutar lekhochla beShabbos. This
event, see, even the original event came from not being sensitive and
not responding and so on, and only learning, of course, this maidservant
had to lose her eye in the equation. But it's so interesting,
right, that this people, everybody's like dismissing the importance until it applies
to them or until they actually experience, you know, have some immediate
experience of it. You're allowed to apply this salve on שבת. Shabbos.
And now the גמרא Gemara says a very important, well, it's, the
next couple words have, are halakhically significant, very, it says, מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, why? It's just an
eye. דשוריינא דעינא באובנתא דליבא תלו, deshuryana de'eina be'uvnata deliba talu, because
like the tendons of the eyes are connected to the chambers of
the heart. How do they translate that? You'll tell me when you
catch up.
Anyway, the eye is connected with the
muscles of the heart.
So they don't know what it means.
Right, so obviously doesn't know what it means, but besides which, here
becomes an extremely critical discussion in הלכה. halacha. Is the גמרא Gemara
saying that risk of a limb is itself enough reason to violate
שבת, Shabbos, even though it's not פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, risk of
a limb is also weighty enough to violate שבת? Shabbos? Or what
this next, you could have said that way, but these next last
few words seem to be saying you only violate שבת Shabbos because
risk of an eye could lead to risk of life. Okay. And
then it would mean that in principle risk of a limb you
don't violate שבת Shabbos for. Now I should tell you, first of
all, the המאירי ha-Meiri actually brackets those words and the מאירי Meiri
actually says that you violate שבת Shabbos for risk of a limb.
It doesn't have to be risk of life. And in practice in
הלכה, halacha, although in practice we say, no, risk of a limb
is not enough, it has to be risk of life, pretty much,
you know, the rule is any risk of limb we treat as
a potential risk of life. Because you know, any loss of some
type of a limb of the body is going to potentially have
complications and infections and whatever. So in practice we're pretty much say
that any risk of limb you're מחלל שבת mechaleil Shabbos for. Okay,
we treat
it... is do we do it because intrinsically we say it overrides
שבת shabbos or because we say we see it as connected to
a risk of life? Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says like this: How much of a שבת shabbos if you're missing
limbs?
Well, how much of that's true, but it's not much of a
life, I mean not that I should
say that חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, but I'm just
saying these people all work with their hands, physical, you know, those
were most of the jobs. It's not just that. I mean, it's
an eye for God's sake. Okay, it's also it impacts the rest
of your life. Okay, so that's why you would want to say
that that's big enough that maybe that alone you're מחלל שבת mechallel
shabbos for. Okay, but it's interesting that the גמרא gemara frames it
in terms of risk of life. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says like this: כגון מאי, kagon mai, so now what type of
eye infections are considered or eye issues are considered serious enough that
you would violate
שבת? shabbos? אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda כגון רירא kagon rira
which is some type of like of a pus type of or
whatever, some type of a what's it called, something is you know
liquid is coming out of it. דייצא daitsa which is a I
don't even know...
stabbing pain in the eye...
stabbing pain. דמא, dama, דמא dama blood coming out. דימעתא dimata I
guess uncontrollable tearing, and וקדחא v'kidcha is an inflammation.
ותחילת אוכלא v'tchilas uchla that's only at the beginning of the sort
of of the fever. לאפוקי סוף אוכלא l'apukei sof uchla but if
the thing is healing and it's red and it's inflamed or whatever
but it's obviously at the healing stage, then you would not violate
שבת. shabbos. ופצוחי עינא u'ptzuchei aina and if it's פצוחי עינא ptzuchei
aina which רש"י Rashi says is what do they say that it
is? Oh, you're just doing it, you want to put on the
salve in order like to you know to help your vision but
it's not actually some type of a of an inflammation or some
type of a you know of a problem then דלא d'lo you're
not allowed to. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda זיבורא zibora if
we're dealing with a wasp
sting, okay, ודחארזי v'dacharzei what is this or a puncture from some
type of a you know of a of a thorn. סילא sila
or is a what is this... oh no that is a puncture
of a thorn. Right. Either oh either a puncture of like of
like a hook or of like a nail or of a
thorn. וסמטא v'simta we had וסמטא v'simta before... blister... what was that?
Oh yeah, blister. ודחייב ליה עינא v'chaiv lei aina and if you've
got a problem with your eye ואתי אילויי אשתא v'asi iluyei eshta
or somebody has a fever. So if you have any of these
problems, we're not now talking about שבת shabbos issues back to health
issues, כולהו בי בנאי סכנתא. kulhu bei banai sakanta. For all these
things, it's a danger to go into the bathhouse, okay? I guess
too much heat and steam or whatever's not going to be good
for it. חמי לחמי chami l'chami and now if what should you
do? So this sounds like something hot for something hot. But actually
רש"י Rashi's גירסא girsa seems to be חמי chami with an א.
alef. And he reads it that's like a radish. You have you
have like some type of a problem with some type of a
fever or inflammation, eat a radish. וסילקא v'silka and beet לצינא l'tzina
something if you have something that's like a problem about something being
too cold or okay that'll warm you up, the beet. וחילופא סכנתא
v'chilufa sakanta and if you reverse it, it'll be a danger. חמימי
לעקרבא chamimi l'akraba now you put hot water if you have a
scorpion sting
וקרירי לזיבורתא v'kariri l'ziburta and you have some cold compress if you
have a wasp sting. וחילופא סכנתא v'chilufa sakanta and if you reverse
it, it is a danger. And I guess we'll read one more:
חמימי לסילא chamimi l'sila hot water for some type of a of
a what do you call it, of a thorn puncture
וקרירי v'kariri and cold compress
לחספניתא l'chaspunisa which is some type of a crack on the face
וחילופא סכנתא v'chilufa sakanta and the reverse will be a danger and
we will continue with these rabbinic medicinal treatments tomorrow and move on
to other things.